Inventory of the Virginia Cole Trenholm Papers, 1929-1979
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
- PHOTOGRAPHS:
  - Black and white photographs (5X7) made from slides, labeled as follows:
    - 34) The Overland Telegraph Line was finished along the Emigrant Trail, in 1861, but the Sioux became so hostile along the Platte the following year that freighters and emigrants were rerouted an another trail going through Colorado and following a so-called Cherokee Trail over the Laramie Plains and westward. The trail was given its name because a band of Cherokees followed its course in going to California during the gold rush. The new trail avoided the Sioux, but it went through Arapahoe country in the Medicine Bow area (PHOTO (T681-ch) Trail-Cherokee)
    - 35) These emigrants are seen along the Overland Stage Route, as the new trail was known (PHOTO (T681-ch) Trail-Cherokee)
    - 36) This tepee belonged to Little Raven, head chief of the Southern Araphoes. When he saw that trouble was brewing at Sand Creek (in Colorado) he folded his tent and went down the Arkansas. His subchief Left Hand was ill at the time, so he remained at Fort Lyon. Just what became of him is still a matter of conjecture. It is not known whether he was killed during the attack or that he joined Little Raven. Though he was reportedly killed, the Left Hand who became chief after Little Raven answers to his description (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap) Indian-Tribe-Araphoe)
    - 37) The major battle of 1865, "the bloody year on the plains", took place at Platte Bridge. This is reconstructed Fort Caspar. The survivors of the attack at Sand Creek on an unarmed camp of Cheyennes and Arapahoes did not wait for spring to retaliate. In January, after making two devastating raids on Julesburg, Colorado, they swept northward into Wyoming (PHOTO (F775-cas) Fort-Caspar)
    - 38) Red Cloud was so incensed when he discovered the white man freighting in supplies to build forts on the Bozeman Trail through his Powder River hunting grounds that he refused to take part in the council. Three forts were constructed, but they were under constant siege. Red Cloud would not talk peace until the forts were abandoned (PHOTO (B-R245-c) Red Cloud)
    - 39) The Indians called Fort Phil Kearny "the hated fort on the Little Piney". The Fetterman Massacre, near the fort, was the major incident during the Red Cloud War, 1866. When the three posts were abandoned, Red Cloud reluctantly came to Fort Laramie, where he signed the Treaty of 1868, removing the Sioux from Wyoming to South Dakota (PHOTO (F775-pk) Fort - Phil Kearny)
    - 40) Little Shield, a well known Arapahoe chief, was for many years the mascot of the Plains Hotel in Cheyenne, Wyoming. His picture was on its official stationary and napkins; his likeness, immortalized in the tile floor; and his profile, emblazoned on a neon sign (PHOTO (B-L727-s) Little Shield)
    - 41) Chief Cut Nose is tapping his left breast to indicate he is a Northern Arapahoe. He is shown here in council with Gen. W. S. Hancock (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap) Indian-Tribe-Araphoe)
    - 42) Medicine Man, pictured with his family, was head chief of the Northern Arapahoe before they were placed on the reservation in 1878. The Shoshones, who finally sued the government for the land the Arapahoes had occupied on a "temporary" basis 60 years, won their case and were paid. Since 1938, the reservation has been jointly owned by the two tribes (PHOTO (B-H468-m) Medicine Man)
    - 43) The Medicine Lodge Treaty Council (1867) was designed to relocate the Cheyennes and Arapahoes displaced by the debacle at Sand Creek. The two tribes had previously relinquished their land "between the rivers" for a reservation at Sand Creek. This was managed throught the Fort Wise Treaty. Once again, the Indians were to be moved. The woman in the artist's sketch is Maggie Poisal Fitzpatrick, the Arapahoe wife of Thomas Fitzpatrick, first agent for the Platte River tribes (the Sioux, Cheyenne, and Arapahoe) and the Southern on the Arkansas. Little Raven insisted on having her as an interpreter as she was the only one he could trust - he had been lied to many times (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap))
    - PHOTOGRAPHS: 44) Cheyenne and Arapahoe Indians attending the Fort Laramie Treaty Council of 1868 with the "Seven Wise Men of the Great White Father" the Peace Commisioners. (PHOTO (F775-la-in) Fort-Laramie-Indians)
    - 45) Buffalo were still plentiful enough to stop the trains when the railroad was built through Wyoming in 1868-69 (PHOTO (W646-buf) Wildlife-Buffalo)
    - 46) The aboriginal domain of the Shoshones and Bannock is diminished into the Wind River Reservation (in black) and the Fort Hall Reservation (in white) (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh) Indian-Tribe-Shoshone)
    - 47) This map of the Wind River Reservation shows the Riverton Irrigation Project in the large white area. Riverton, a municipality, is actually on the reservation. Lander is just below the southern border (PHOTO (In2) Indian)
    - 48) The old Block House, where ammunition was stored, is the last landmark at Camp Brown, later renamed Fort Washakie in honor of the chief. Prior to Camp Brown, there was a camp at the present site of Lander, known as Camp Augur. It was established for the protection of the Shoshones, who were harassed by the Platte River Indians (PHOTO (In2-res-wi) Indian-Reservation-Wind River)
    - 49) Charlie Washakie, son of the chief, was an outstanding artist. Here is his hide painting of his father's exploits (PHOTO (B-W27) Washakie)
    - 50) Thomas Fitzpatrick discovered a foundling along the trail, so he named him Friday for the day he was found and sent him to St. Louis to be educated. He later returned to his tribe and served as an interpreter and a peace chief (PHOTO (B-F912) Friday)
    - 51) Dr. James Irwin, agent at the Wind River Reservation in 1878, is pictured with a delegation of Northern Arapahoes who came with their peace pipes to request that they be allowed to reside on the reservation. Chief Black Coal (Tag-ge-tha-the, Shot-Off-Fingers) proudly displays his battle scars (PHOTO (B-B561-co) Black Coal)
    - 52) Official picture of Black Coal in his warbonnet. Though he was a Catholic convert, an Episcopal Bishop referred to him as the "unsung" hero of the Rockies. He insisted that children attend school and learn the language and ways of the white men (PHOTO (B-B561-co) Black Coal)
    - 53) This is Washakie's best known picture. He once complained that the Arapahoes had "too many chiefs". In his long life he saw many come and go. When he finally died at the approximate age of 100 years, he was given a burial with full military honors. He is said to have been the only Indian chief so honored (PHOTO (B-W27) Washakie)
    - 54) The Fletcher family was among those attacked in the vicinity of Arlington, Wyoming, in 1865. A thirteen-year-old girl (Amanda Mary) was abducted by the Cheyennes, her two-year-old sister (Lizzie) by the Arapahoes. Amanda Mary was ransomed about a year or so later, but Lizzie grew up among the Arapahoes, married John Brokenhorn, and had a son, Walks Ahead. Lizzie's Indian name was Kills-in-Time, probably in reference to the fact that her mother was killed at the time of the attack. When Indian names were anglicized she became Sarah and her son Columbus. She is generally referred to as "the White Indian Girl". When she was identified by her sister, she refused to admit she was white, though she had red hair, fair skin, and freckles. She lived out her life among the Arapahoes and she never learned to speak English (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap) Indian-Tribe-Araphoe)
    - 55) In 1881, a group of children were rounded up and taken from the Wind River Reservation to Carlisle Indian School in Pennsylvania. The Arapahoes, bearing such names as Shakespeare, Lincoln, and Gerfield, outnumbered the Shoshones, here shown in hats. Acculturation - the imposition of the white culture on the Indian - was now underway (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap) Indian-Tribe-Araphoe)
    - 56) When President Arthur visited the reservation in 1883, the Shoshones and Araphoes dressed up to meet him. Black Coal is seen on the back row, far right, but Washakie is missing. He remained in his lodge because, according to his idea of Indian protocol, the President should come to see him, which he did (PHOTO (B-B561-co) Black Coal)
    - 57) In 1883, Reverend John Roberts came from Wales to the reservation as a missionary. He had requested that he be sent to the wildest tribe in the country. When he arrived, the only thing wild he found was the weather. It was 60 degrees below zero (PHOTO (B-R542-j) Roberts, John)
    - 58) This is the first school house and mission on the Wind River Reservation. It still stands in the Shoshone Cemetary west of Fort Washakie (PHOTO (In2-res-wi) Indian-Reservation-Wind River)
    - 59) Reverend Roberts had a boarding school for girls. To keep from being lonesome, a tepee was erected in the yard (PHOTO (In2-res-wi) Indian-Reservation-Wind River)
    - 60) Rev. Sherman, center, with Standing Horse, left and Black Coal. Coolidge, a full-blooded Arapahoe, was raised and educated for the ministry by and army officer whose name he took. He was working under Reverand Roberts when he suggested that he find out if his people in the upper area of the Arapahoe side of the reservation would like to have an Episcopal mission. There answer was, "Ethete", meaning good. This was the name of the post office at the mission (PHOTO (B-B561-co) Black Coal)
    - 61) St. Michael's Mission at Ethete is built in the form of a camp circle (PHOTO (In2-mis-smm) Indian-Mission-St. Michael's Mission)
    - 62) Since the Episcopal Church was already established on the reservation, it was assigned to that church in line with the policy at that time. A year later the Catholics arrived. The agent suggested that the priest establish a mission among the Araphoes, with St. Stephens eventually resulting. This is the main building which houses, among other things, the post office, St. Stephens, Wyoming (PHOTO (In2-mis-smm) Indian-Mission-St. Stephens Mission)
    - 63) The Catholic Church at St. Stephens was painted white by the teenagers, then decorated inside and out by Raphael Norse, a talented Arapahoe artist. The Arapahoes use geometric designs in their art work. The "Shoshone Rose" (any flower like object) has almost become a trademark of the Wind River Shoshones (PHOTO (In2-mis-smm) Indian-Mission-St. Stephens Mission)
    - 64) Ethete also has a Catholic Church, decorated by Norse (PHOTO (In2-mis-em) Indian-Mission-Ethete Mission))
    - 65) Around 1890, the Ghost Dance "craze" swept the Indian country, with the Fort Washakie serving as a point of diffusion. The ritualistic Arapahoes entered the spirit of it enthusiastically, but the Shoshones were skeptical. Wovoka, a Nevada Paiute, started the movement which ended in tragedy for the Sioux at Wounded Knee (PHOTO (B-W917) Wovoka))
    - 66) Sitting Bull, a Northern Arapahoe, took the concept to the South, where the Indians took part by the thousands. He was second only to Wovoka until Wooden Lance, a Kiowa, challenged him to debate. Sitting Bull, who was defeated, was succeeded by Black Coyote, who continued to believe until the concept finally died out in the South just as Capt. Hugh L. Scott predicted it would. He had been sent by the government to investigate (PHOTO (B-Si88-b) Sitting Bull)
    - 67) The Ghost Dance concept was based on the belief that if the Indians danced the Naroya-a sliding sidestep - for three days, sang the prescribed songs, and used the paint, the dead Indians and buffalo would return and the white man would disappear. This gave hope to a discouraged peopled until they became disillusioned (PHOTO (In2-da-od) Indian-Oaohee-Ghost Dance)
    - 68) The Ghost Dance shirt was thought to be impervious to bullets (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap) Indian-Tribe-Araphoe)
    - 69) This is a Peyote Cult meeting, drawn by Carl Sweezy, a gifted Southern Arapahoe artist. The Water Woman brings in water as part of the ceremony. The cult had its beginning in the South. It is believed to have flourished some time before it was brought to the Wind River Reservation by William Shakespeare, an Arapahoe. The Shoshones practiced the Comanche and Kiowa ways, the Arapahoes, the Arapahoe - that is, until became standardized by the Native American Church. Peyote is used as a sacrament, just as wine in the white man's church (PHOTO (In2-pey) Indian-Peyote Ceremony)
    - 70) Sharp Nose, who was head chief of the Northern Arapahoes after Black Coal, was the last chief to retain his Indian name without change, and his two wives, until his death. He died in 1900, the same year as Washakie (PHOTO (B-Sh23-n) Sharp Nose)
    - 71) Two Arapahoes at Carlisle Indian School are shown doing "squaw work", and they do not seem too happy about it (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap) Indian-Tribe-Araphoe)
    - 72) This excellent acculturation picture shows an Arapahoe dressed in white man's attire in an effort to conform. The two Cheyennes are relaxed in their native dress (PHOTO (B-B863-m) Buffalo Meat)
    - 73) Yellow Calf was the last recognized Arapahoe chief. When names were anglicized, he was given the name George Caldwell, which he used for legal matters only. The Indians did not have surnames, so the name of the head of the family was considered the family name, unless in translated form it might be objectionable. A first name was then added (PHOTO (B-438-c) Washakie-Family)
    - 74) The McLaughlin Agreement if 1904 further diminished the reservation. Previously the southern part had tobe relinquished to satisfy mining claims. Sherman Coolidge, in overcoat, looks in while Yellow Calf signs (PHOTO (B-W27-f) Washakie-Family)
    - 75) The Sun Dance did not originate with the Arapahoes, but they perfected it. They call the Sun Dance Lodge the Offerings Lodge, with the Center Pole representing Man Above, or the Supreme Power. The scarves hanging from the overhead beams are symbolic of the offerings brought to the ceremony. The Shoshones and the Arapahoes have their own Sun Dances (PHOTO (In2-da-sh) Indian-Dance-Shoshone)
    - 76) This is believed to be Chief Washakie's last picture (PHOTO (B-W27) Washakie)
    - 77) In the 1920s Tim McCoy organized a group of Arapahoes to take part in the "Covered Wagon" movie. This picture was taken on the steps of the Wyoming State Capitol. Lizzie Brokenhorn is on the front row in her warbonnet (PHOTO (In2-tri-arap) Indian-Tribe-Araphoe)
    - 78) Since Wyoming is known as the Equality State, it is interesting to note that Irene Kinnear Meade was the first woman on the Shoshone Tribal Council, in 1930. She also had the distinction of being a charter member of the Wyoming Mayflower Society, through her father Napoleon Bonaparte Kinnear. She was the ganddaughter of Jim Baker and Meateetse (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh) Indian-Tribe-Shoshone)
    - 79) Nellie Scott, whose mother was a foundling on the battlefield, did not know which tribe she belonged to, but she was on the Shoshone roll at first. Then she was dropped because of a technicality and picked up by Yellow Calf on the Arapahoe. In 1935, she was the first woman on the Arapahoe Tribal Council, where she served for 37 years (PHOTO (B-Sco85-n) Scott, Nellie)
    - 80) When the symbolic wagon train went through Shoshone country in the fall of 1975, on its way to Fort Laramie to spend the winter, it made camp on the Sweetwater. There the Shoshones entered the Bicentennial spirit by pitching their tepees along the stream as they did in pre-reservation times. It was reminiscent of Alfred Jacob Miller's painting, "Shoshone Hospitality". It ever so briefly, history repeated itself (PHOTO (In2-tri-sh) Indian-Tribe-Shoshone)
- MISCELLANEOUS:
  - Accomodations Information - Tsa-la-gi Area (Box 5)
  - Bibliography of Cherokees (2) (Box 5)
  - Cherokee National Historical Society, Inc. The Cherokee National Museum (2) (Box 5)
  - Diagram-Organization of Wyoming Government (Box 5)
  - Envelope-Hotel Plains (Box 5)
  - Fact Sheet-Cherokee National Historical Society, Inc. Tsa-la-gi. July 1974 (2), July 1975 (1), 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - Library Index Card: The Shoshonis, Sentinels of the Rockies, by Virginia Cole Trenholm (Box 5)
  - List of persons honoured by the Midwest Region (Box 5)
  - Postcard: Medicine Lodge Stockade (Box 5)
  - Program Fact Sheet - Tsa-la-gi, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Selected List of Portaits of Prominent Indians (Box 5)
  - Booklet: WHEATLAND'S FIRST CHURCH, by Virginia Cole Trenholm. In Commemoration of the 62nd Anniversary Union Congregational Church Wheatland, Wyoming, July 7, 1957. Reprinted from ANNALS OF WYOMING, April 1957 ((C47-con-ww) Church-Congregational-Wheatland, wyo.)
  - Manuscript: "The Wind River Indians", a lecture delivered before the Albany County Historical Society, Laramie, Wyoming, by Virginia Cole Trenholm. Xerox copy of her notes with annotations, May 17, 1971 ((B-T723vc))
  - Booklet: "Amanda Mary and the Dog Soldiers", by Virginia Cole Trenholm. Reprinted from ANNALS OF WYOMING, Vol. 46, No. 1, Spring 1974. The Lusk Herald, Lusk, Wyoming ((B-T723-vc))